<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of housebandrie, no lesse profitable then delectable declaryng how by the housebandrie, or rather housewiferie of hennes, for fiue hundreth Frankes or Frenche poundes (making in Englishe money lv.£i. xi.s̄. i.d.) once emploied, one maie gaine in the yere, fower thousande and fiue hundreth Frankes (whiche in Englishe money, maketh fiue hundreth pou[n]des) of honest profite: All costes and charges deducted. Written in the Frenche tongue by Maister Prudent Choselat. And lately translated into English by R.E.</title>
            <title>Discours oeconomique non moins utile que recreatif. English</title>
            <author>Prudent Le Choyselat, M.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1577</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10175</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20452</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101197</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837019</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837019</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1323</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10175)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1323)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 971:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of housebandrie, no lesse profitable then delectable declaryng how by the housebandrie, or rather housewiferie of hennes, for fiue hundreth Frankes or Frenche poundes (making in Englishe money lv.£i. xi.s̄. i.d.) once emploied, one maie gaine in the yere, fower thousande and fiue hundreth Frankes (whiche in Englishe money, maketh fiue hundreth pou[n]des) of honest profite: All costes and charges deducted. Written in the Frenche tongue by Maister Prudent Choselat. And lately translated into English by R.E.</title>
                  <title>Discours oeconomique non moins utile que recreatif. English</title>
                  <author>Prudent Le Choyselat, M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Jhon Kyngston, for Myles Jenynges, dvvellyng in Paules Churche-yarde, at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1577.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by R.E., of: M. Prudent le Choyselat. Discours oeconomique non moins utile que recreatif.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A profitable discourse of housebandrie.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]¹ B-D⁴ E² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Williams College. Chapin Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chicken industry --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1323:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOVRSE OF HOVSEBANDRIE, No leſſe profitable then delectable: declaryng how by the Houſebandrie, or rather Houſewiferie of Hennes, for fiue hundreth Franks or Frenche poundes (making in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe money iv. li. xj. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. j.d.) once emploied, one maie gaine in the yere, fower thouſande and fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth Frankes (whiche in Engliſhe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, maketh fiue hundreth pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des) of honeſt profits: All coſtes and charges deducted.</p>
            <p>Written in the Frenche tongue, by Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Prudent Choſelas. And lately tranſlated into Engliſhe by R. E.</p>
            <p>¶ Jmprinted at London by Jhon Kyngston, for Myles Jenynges, dvvellyng in Paules Churche-yarde, at the ſigne of the Bible. 1577.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="rate_of_exchange">
            <pb facs="tcp:1323:2"/>
            <p>A Souſe, is xij. Frenche pence.</p>
            <p>Xij. Souſe, maked a Frenche Teſton, whiche is fower grotes Engliſhe.</p>
            <p>Three Souſes, make a grote.</p>
            <p>A Franke or Frenche pounde, is twentie Souſes, xviij. Souſes, makes it. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. after ix. Souſesto a ſhillyng. So remaineth of the Franke twoo Soules, to make vp the Franke of twentie Souſes.</p>
            <p>ix. Frenche pence, make one Engliſhe penie. ix. Souſes, one ſhillyng: ix. Frankes one Engliſhe pounde: nyne hundreth, one hundrethinyne thouſande, one thouſande.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1323:2"/>
            <head>To the right honourable the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee <hi>of Rochefort, Knight of the order of</hi> the Kyng, and Capitaine of fiue hundreth menne of Armes of his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunces.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lorde, hauyng from my youthe in memore the precepte of <hi>Apelles,</hi> moste excellent Painter of his tyme, who commaunded his Prentices not to paſſe one daie, without drawyng of a line, to the ende to keepe theim in breath and continuance (as doeth the Hunter his Greyhounde) he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by that precepte to ſhewe howe greately idleneſſe is to bee auoided, and howe greate is the loſſe of tyme, to leaue the exerciſe of trauaile. And therefore, not to tranſgreſſe this precepte in theſe tumuliuous and turbulente ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, copoſed of more then ciuile warres in the bowells of France, I haue addreſſed my ſelf for the auoidyng of Idleneſſe, to drawe my line vpon an humble and lowe ſubiect, to make a diſcourſe of domeſticall Houſbandry. &amp; to ſhewe how a diligent man maie of one little ſumme, drawe greate games by honeſte me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes. Which doyng, I greately recreate my Spirites emong my bookes, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a greate parte of my ſoron full thoughtes of theſe troublous tymes. And foraſmuche as I knowe, that after long practiſe of armes, and the greate trauaile which you haue had therein, the trauaile of letters ſhalbe greatly delectable vnto to you, when with equall paſe, you ioyne wiſedome with magnanimitie, I haue taken vppon me the boldneſſe, to preſent vnto you this my little labour,
<pb facs="tcp:1323:3"/>by the readyng whereof you maie take one hower of recreation. I haue addreſſed this little Houſbandrie in ſuche order, that the practiſe beyng therein well instructed in buiyng, and conſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thynges bought, with diſcreete distribution of the ſame, maie aſſure hym ſelf to lacke no marchantes. This little diſcourſe, is of the time of the troubles of the yere M.D.LXVII. before that the Winde <hi>Caecias</hi> drewe the cloude of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles into the countries of Poictu and Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunoys, where I appoincted the Marchaunte to make his emploit, as ſhall bee ſene in the readyng.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours moste obeiſant, Prudent Choyſelat.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1323:3"/>
            <head>The Aucthor to his frende afflicted <hi>vvith the troubles of the ciuile VVarres</hi> in Fraunce, in the yere of our Lorde, <hi>M.D.LXVII.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He calamities and encombraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the miſeries and ſorrowes, whiche proceede of he inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie into the whiche the people of this tyme is plonged in this age of Iron (Of Iron I maie ſaie, hardened to miſfortune) hath well witneſſed to vs, how true is the aunciente Prouerbe, whiche ſaith: That <hi>Iupiter</hi> is ſlowe to viſite the ſkinne of the Gote: Yet that in fine, he permitteth not an euill facte vnpuniſhed. Wee haue ſeen with our eyes, and felte by effecte in oure Fraunce, at the riſyng of theſe laſte troubles, fallyng vpon vs like te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt of a Haile vnlooked for. The whiche, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng out of the Boxe of <hi>Pandora,</hi> or out of a broken infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Priſon, was ſo ſpredde emong menne, and hath made ſuche ouerture of vice and miſchief, that all ſortes of euill are ſette at libertie: <hi>Mars</hi> the Executour of the wrathe of the Goddes, hath ſo vomited his Choler without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that the burnyng thereof hath chafed theim, not onely to ſociall Warres, but to all Deueliſhe attemptes, more then <hi>Megarique</hi> to Robberies and Murthers, and (as ſaieth <hi>Cicero</hi>) to <hi>Phalariſmes</hi> and moſte cruell inhumanites, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulcan</hi> leauyng his proper Region, hath folowed theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, and ſearched newe habitations, to exerciſe theſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations: In ſuche ſorte that it is eaſie to iudge, that theſe miſhappes are fallen emong menne, to putte theim in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of their ſynnes, founde in the ſaied Gotes ſkinne, of the whiche you haue paied your lotte: as I haue knowen by the complaintes, whiche you haue made for your greate loſſes of money and menage ſpeiled and deſtroied by ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cage,
<pb facs="tcp:1323:4"/>and pillage alſo of your Nobles. In the whiche I la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente your fortune, as a common Shipwracke: But paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>te ſurmount. And to helpe you, I haue none other meane then by aduiſe and counſaile: you knowe that all my life, I haue ſpente little tyme in hourdyng of richeſſe, and thynges caduke. And that rather I tooke pleaſure to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my Spirites, in readyng and ſearchyng of ſuche thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as fewe menne haue founde. Yet not to refuſe the helpe a freende in neceſſitie: and vnderſtandyng that there yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth vnto you, fiue or ſixe hundreth Frankes, whiche you haue hidden, foreſeyng ſo greate a miſchaunce, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto me, to the ende that you in nothyng diminiſhe your ſtate of liuyng, ſo to redreſſe the ſame, that you maye eaſely in ſhorte tyme, reenter into as greate and ample re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes, as you had before the ſaied troubles.</p>
            <p>Your reuenewe doubtleſſe conſiſteth in Houſebandrie of all ſortes of cattaile, as Beeues, Kyne, Mares, Sheepe, Foule, and ſuche other thynges as reioyſeth theim, whiche are giuen to the Countrie life. I can bee a witneſſe how your Table was euer readie for your familiar freendes: And your wife and daughter were of worſhipfull eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and of carefull prouiſion for you famelie, entertained by honeſt ſparyng and frugalitie, requiſite in due tyme and ſeaſon. At whiche tyme alſo you were well eſtemed, for your liberalitie toward your neighbours and freendes. But ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng that Fortune hath tourned her viſage (as ſhe is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to doe, when the tyme agreeth with her) you muſte needes retire, and not ſuffer her to remaine with you in like regarde as before. And therefore you muſte forgette thoſe loſſes, and thinke of a Baine to come: To the whiche you ſhall attaine eaſely, with this little ſumme remainyng, if you will emploie it, as I will aduertiſe you. And this without ſpotte of villanie, or filthie and exceſſiue gaines. Furthermore, your Houſebandrie ſhall floriſhe, and your name ſhall bee more knowen in Fraunce, then was emong
<pb facs="tcp:1323:4"/>the Greekes, the name of hym that burnte the Temple of <hi>Diana</hi> in <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to make no longer diſcourſe: aduiſe your ſelf to be ſtowe your ſumme of money in buiyng of Hennes: not <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagrides,</hi> the whiche <hi>Bellomus</hi> in his Peregrination affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be our Hennes of the Indies (beyng the true gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieres of Dtes) but common Hennes of our Countrie: and Houſebande or employe them in ſuche ſort, as I will ſhewe hereafter. And bee not impacient to attende the concluſion.</p>
            <p>Firſte of all, it is neceſſarie to haue them, neare vnto the Citée of Paris, famous and of greate renoume throughout all the worlde, to bee the marte and ſeate of all good Artes, and Sciences, and populous of all ſortes of menne, if there bee any other vnder the Sunne. There conſider the ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome commodious place well builded, hauyng good roomes and Stables, with a Courte or yarde incloſed of twoo Acres of grounde, more or leſſe, and walled of ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente height. With alſo twoo other Acres incloſed, for an other purpoſe, whereof wee will ſpeake hereafter. Of theſe are enowe to bee founde, in the olde rurall buildynges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Citie of Paris. So then can you not ſaie, that you are ſtaightly lodged. For <hi>Quintus Cincinnatus</hi> Citezine of Roome (ſo named for wearyng his haire combed and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) poſſeſſed no more when he was called to the dignitie of <hi>Dictator,</hi> as writeth <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alerius Maximus</hi> in his fowerth booke.</p>
            <p>The aforeſaied Mannour place or Ferme, with Yarde or Courte incloſed, you ſhall take by Leaſe for certaine yeres, paiyng yerely rent for the dwellyng of you and your famelie. You ſhall diſpoſe your ſtables commodiouſlie for your Hennes and Chickins, with the viewe or proſpecte to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the Winter Drient, that the Sunne maie giue the good morrowe to your Hennes, whiche greately delite at the Mornyng Sunne, as noteth <hi>Columella</hi> in his ix. booke of Houſebandrie: alſo <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arre</hi> in his third booke.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1323:5"/>The Henne houſes, ſhall bée commodious and profitable if thei bee alone or ſolitarie, and the Plankes well couered with claye, becauſe the Hennes delite to pruine and toum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them ſelues in duſte, and to bee kept warme. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore boordes or plaiſter, are not conuenient to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The Lathers or Perches muſte bee from the grounde twoo foote high. Alſo flatte, and not rounde, becauſe the Hennes doe not bende, or crooke their clawes or Talantes as doe other graſpelyng foules.</p>
            <p>The ſaied Henne houſes alſo, in the daie tyme muſte bee open, that thei maie be euented with Winde and Aire. And that the Night aire maie more eaſely tranſpire and breath out, that it maie cauſe no diſeaſe by cloſe ayre, whiche in ſhorte tyme cauſeth putrefaction, and diſeaſes thereof pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceadyng.</p>
            <p>Vnder the Henne houſes, and all aboute the Stables, ſhall bee hanged many Panyers of conueniente bigneſſe, ſtufte with Haye, to receiue the Hennes when thei laye. For Haye in this caſe, is muche better then Strawe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſofter and warmer, and is not ſo apte to enge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der Lice or Woormes. I dooe not meane that it ſhould bee ſo deare as was that, whiche was ſolde for fower <hi>Attiques</hi> the handfull, for menne to eate, at the tyme of the greate Famin in Ieruſalem, as writeth <hi>Ioſephus</hi> in his ſeuenth booke of the warre of the Iewes, the fower <hi>Attiques</hi> amountyng to fowertene Frenche Soules,<note place="margin">xviij. d. and ij. thirdes.</note> after three Souſes and ſixe Frenche Pence for a Souſe, as muche as the Romaine peuie, as writeth learned <hi>Budaeus</hi> in his booke <hi>De Aſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When you haue thus diſpoſed your Henne houſes, and made theim ſure and ſaufe againſt all hurtfull beaſtes and Vermine, that maie enter by Daie or Night, and haue well placed the Paniers, to receiue and harbour theim, you ſhall beſtowe the ſumme of three hundreth Frankes, in buiyng of good Hennes, whiche maie coſt you after the rate of fiue Souſes (whiche is vj. d. and twoo-thirdes) the peece, by
<pb facs="tcp:1323:5"/>reaſon of the dearthe whiche is now, by occaſion of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. Whiche ſhall bee twelue hundreth Hennes, after xxv. Frankes the hundred.<note place="margin">xxv. Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes iv. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vj. d. &amp; ij. thirdes of j. d.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Countries of Angeou, Touraine, and Lodunois, haue been the Countries with Britaigne, leſſe troubled with the ſaied Ciuile warres: And therefore Hennes are there better cheape: Alſo verie good, ſtrong, well membe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and of the beſte race to make your emploite.</p>
            <p>You ſhall chooſe the youngeſte, whiche are apter to laye then the olde: and the common, more then thei of kynde: or the Blacke, Redde, and Taunie, whiche are more fruitefull then the Graie or White, as <hi>Aristotle</hi> affirmeth in his Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie of Beaſtes in the firſte booke, the firſte Chapiter. And alſo thei whiche haue their creſte or combe double and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, as witneſſeth <hi>Plinie</hi> in his naturall Hiſtorie. Alſo <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladius</hi> and <hi>Petrus Creſcenſis</hi> in his Booke of Houſebandrie. Likewiſe <hi>Carolus Stephanus</hi> a man of our tyme, &amp; a diligent gatherer of thinges Economike, parteinyng to Houſholde and Houſebandrie.</p>
            <p>Thei of meane bigneſſe, are the beſte, hauyng their breſt large, their bodie well fleſhed, not with long Spurres like vnto Cockes, for thei commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly breake their Egges. Take héede alſo that thei bee not to fatte. Witneſſe the good wife whiche beyng in loue with her Henne, fedde her ſo well, and made her ſo fatte, that ſhe lefte laiyng, as rehearſeth <hi>Eſope</hi> in his Fables.</p>
            <p>You ought to thinke that the good Woman loued her Henne no leſſe, then the Emperour <hi>Honorius,</hi> ſonne of <hi>Theo doſius</hi> loued his, named Rome. Who vnderſtanding that <hi>Alaricus</hi> Kyng of the Gothes had taken Rome, (whiche was the aunciente Citee of Rome) was verie ſadde, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng that <hi>Alaricus</hi> had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Henne, whiche he ſo muche loued, as <hi>Zonar</hi> the Greke Hiſtoriographer hath written, in the life of <hi>Honorius.</hi> I ſaie the aunciente Rome, becauſe the Emperours of the Eaſt partes, called Conſtantinople,
<pb facs="tcp:1323:6"/>newe Rome.</p>
            <p>In like maner you ſhall buye Cockes, to ſorte or matche them. Sixe ſcore Cockes ſhall ſuffice for the twelue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth Hennes.<note place="margin">v. pi. vi. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. viij. d.</note> For one Cocke, maie ſuffice for tenne Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Thei maie coſte you tenne Souſes the peece, ouer and aboue the price of the Hennes: which amounteth to four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and eight Frankes. Thei of the age from a yere and a halfe, vnto twoo yeres, are the beſte.</p>
            <p>To knowe them well, you ſhall conſider the Plumage or Feathers. The Blacke, Redde, and Taunie, are the beſte. Alſo thei that haue their Combe or Creſt vpright, and dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or diuided. Their eyes Redde and gliſteryng: Their becke, ſhorte and hooked: well ſuprred: their goyng, hautie and proude: Their voice ſtrong and ſoundyng: And ſuche as crowe muche, repreſentyng ſuche a maieſtie, as did the Cocke of the Perſians, whiche emong them was reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and honoured for a Kyng, as reciteth <hi>Aristophanes.</hi> At the leaſt, that thei ſhewe a certain hardineſſe, as thei whiche the <hi>Carians,</hi> people of the leſſe <hi>Aſia,</hi> bore vpon their Morion or Helmet, goyng to battaile: As <hi>Alexander de Alexandro</hi> hath written in the xx. Chapiter of his firſte booke.</p>
            <p>And if you will take pleaſure in Diuination of thynges to come,<note place="margin">Alectoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantia.</note> by Cockes, (whiche Dinination is named <hi>Alecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romantia</hi>) as did <hi>Iamblicus</hi> maiſter of <hi>Proclus,</hi> as <hi>Libanius</hi> his compaignion, greate and learned Philoſophers, in the tyme of the Emperour <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alens,</hi> you maie make experiment of ſuche predictions, and therewith dooe pleaſure to your freendes.</p>
            <p>And to the ende that you ſhall not bee ignoraunte in the Theorike, or ſpeculation of the ſaied Diuination, I will ſhewe you a certaine practiſe and Prognoſtication thereof. Certaine greate lordes were curious to knowe, who ſhould bee ſucceſſour to the Empire, after <hi>Valens,</hi> fauourer of the damnable ſecte of the Arrians: Praiyng the ſaied Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers to giue aunſwere, accordyng to their Arte and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience,
<pb facs="tcp:1323:6"/>whiche thei had of ſuche thynges. Who were verie diligente to ſatiſfie their requeſte, as commonlie menne of letters are not ingrate to communicate to others, the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of their garden.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Iamblicus,</hi> and <hi>Libanius,</hi> choſe a place verie plaine and equall, of conuenient largeneſſe: and cauſed fine pouder, or aſhes to bee ſifted therein. In the whiche pouder, thei wrote the xxiiij. letters of the Alphabet equallie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunt the one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> th'other, one little cubite aſunder, whiche is a foote and a halfe.</p>
            <p>Theſe xxiiij. letters ſo written and ordred, made a figure pentagon, or of fiue angles, hauyng fiue equall diſtaunces. Vpon euery of the whiche letters, thei laied tenne graines, one of Wheate, and an other of Barleye.</p>
            <p>The figure beyng ſet in order, thei toke a Corke, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aied to hym theſe wordes: Cocke enuious, Cockeielous, Cocke proude: Eate the grain, and leaue the letter. Then makyng a greate whiſperyng, in maner of a Charme, thei lette the cocke ſo charmed, eate certaine of the graines liyng vpon the letters. The which letters then ioyned togither, and ſet in order, according to the graines whiche la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe letters were founde. <hi>T,H,E,O,D.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theod.</note> And were thereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to ſearche no further.</p>
            <p>And by this Diuination by the Cocke, the ſaied Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers gaue aunſwere, that the ſucceſſour of the Empire, ſhould bee one <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> or <hi>Theodorus,</hi> or <hi>Theodoius,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Valens</hi> beyng aduertiſed, was greatly diſpleaſed, fearing leaſt his children ſhould bee depriued of the Empire. And therefore putte to death all the greate Lordes, whiche were ſo named <hi>Iambliucs,</hi> had euill fortune, and ſhortly after was poiſoned <hi>Vopiſcus, Lampridius</hi> and <hi>Zonare,</hi> which haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the liues of the Emperours of the Eaſte and Weſte, will make you wiſe in this Prognoſtication.</p>
            <p>Not without reaſon I haue rehearſed vnto you this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Cubite. For if you figure Pentagon were directed by
<pb facs="tcp:1323:7"/>the greate Cubite (whiche is of nyne foote, accordyng to the whiche, the Arke of <hi>Noe</hi> was meaſured, as ſome Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatours haue affirmed,) you might faile in you Diuina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſhall not come to the knowledge of that you deſire.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe, for aſmuche as ſuche Diuinations, be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes, and inchauntmentes of the eyes and ſenſes, hauyng in them no ſubſtaunce of truthe, but rather of lyes, you ſhall giue no faithe thereto. For falſhoode is euer ouercome by by truthe: as by example allegorike, <hi>Ioſephus</hi> in his Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Antiquitie of the Iewes, in the ſeconde Booke and fifth Chapiter declareth: As alſo is written in <hi>Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</hi> Capit. vij. Where the Rodde of <hi>Moiſes,</hi> was by the finger of God tourned into a verie Serpent, and deuoured the fantaſtike Serpentes of the Magicians of <hi>Pharao.</hi> And the Authours of the ſaied Magique, finallie receiued their rewarde as did <hi>Iamblicus:</hi> and as did <hi>Arphaxat</hi> the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian of Perſia, who was ſtriken with a Thumderbolte: As was alſo the Bailiſe of <hi>Maſcon,</hi> whom the Deuill caried awaie, as our Chronicles witneſſeth. And alſo as were <hi>Mathotin</hi> and <hi>Hollere,</hi> Magicians of the Gothes, whiche were ouerwhelmed, as writeth <hi>Olaus Magnus</hi> in his Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Northe Regions, in the third booke. Likewiſe <hi>Oddo</hi> a Magician of Denmarke, who was drouned. And infinite others came to the like euill ende.</p>
            <p>But now to retourne to our Hennes: To entreate theim and gouerne them well, you muſt haue fower ſeruauntes or maides, with large eares, well to conceiue, and vnderſtande your commaundementes: And the feete of Hartes, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligente expedition to execute the ſame: And truſtie right hande, to bée faithfull, loyall, obedience, and of fewe wordes. For (as ſaieth the <hi>Terentian Parmeno</hi>) it is greate faute in ſeruauntes to bee babbelers, and not to keepe their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters counſaill.</p>
            <p>Their office ſhalbe to bryng the Hennes into their bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes euery daie, at fiue of the Clocke in the Eueuyng in So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer:
<pb facs="tcp:1323:7"/>And at three of the Clocke in Winter. Alſo that thei bee diligente to cloſe the entries, and Windowes of the Henne houſes, that in the night, the Foxe (naturall enemie to Hennes) Weaſells, or Polecattes, maie haue no acceſſe. And in the Mornyng, to open the entrees and windowes, that thei maie come foorthe. And then to make cleane the Pearches and Lathers. Alſo to refreaſhe their Pottes and Troughes with cleane water. For filthie and corrupte wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, engendereth the pippe, and other ſickneſſes.</p>
            <p>In the daie alſo, the ſaied ſeruauntes muſte be myndfull, to viſite the Paniers if thei be furniſhed with Haye, and to refreſhe them if neede bee. The whiche muſte be doen euery weeke, for engenderyng of Life, Wormes, and Vermine, whiche make the Hennes leane, and cauſe them to ſcrache.</p>
            <p>In like maner thei muſte bée diligente, in gatheryng the Egges. And by accompt to deliuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a woman, whiche ſhall laye them in older vpon faire wheate ſtrawe, in a place of large and free ayre, to bée kept freſhe and cold. The ſame ſeruauntes, after that in the Mornyng, thei haue giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their feadyng of Barly and Otes, and ſometyntes alſo Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or Tares, ſhall caſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mong theim ſome drie Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounge, to the ende that the Hennes maie labour the more, to ſearche their meate with ſerapyng. For ſucke exerciſe, is wholſome for theim. Then aboute Noone, thei ſhall feede them againe, callyng them with loude voice, that thei maie be acquainted wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the call of their kepers, whom thei will ſone knowe, as did the Sparrowe of <hi>Leſbia Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a:</hi> The Parratte of <hi>Corinna Ouidinna:</hi> The Thruſtle of <hi>Agrippina</hi> the wife of the Emperor <hi>Claudius:</hi> The Rauen of the Sho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker of Roome, whiche gaue the good Morowe to the Emperours <hi>Tiberius, Germanicus,</hi> and <hi>Druſur.</hi> And was bought for xx. <hi>Sesterns,</hi> amountyng to the ſumme of v. hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth crounes of our money, by the ſupputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Budaus,</hi> after the rate of xxv. crounes one <hi>Sesterne.</hi> And in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhall thei doe a little before thei bryng them to rouſte.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1323:8"/>If your yarde containe twoo Acres incloſed, you maye thereof Plowe halfe an Acre in ſome corner, where the He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes maie ſometymes in the daie ſcrape the grounde, and tomble them ſelves in the duſte or ſande, wherein thei take greate pleaſure. You ſhall Plowe or hardle the ſaied lande, once in the moneth, that it become not to hard, that the He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes maie eaſely raiſe it, without hurtyng their clawes.</p>
            <p>You maie alſo caſte certaine ſeedes vppon the Plowed ground, and couer it with the hardle, that the Hennes maie take both more pleaſure and labour, in diſcoueryng it. For the He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes through idleneſſe, become groſſe and heauie, and will ceaſe from laiyng.</p>
            <p>When your Houſebandrie ſhall bee thus well ordered, you muſte practiſe in the Citée of Paris, with ten or twelue Phiſitions, dwellyng in ſundrie places of the ſaied Citée. Not of the beardleſſe and delicate Apollinaries, whiche care for nothyng but glorie, and ciuill flatterie, to get riche Wiues. But of the bearded <hi>AEſculapians,</hi> ſuche as was the Famous Florentine, a man of ſinguler knowledge and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in his doughter, purſued by the vnchaſte loue of <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> kyng of Naples and Hungarie.</p>
            <p>Suche auncient Phiſicions will eaſely permitte the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of Nature, and confirme the wholeſome Edicte of the Emperour <hi>Claildius:</hi> who (as witneſſeth <hi>Suetonius</hi>) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in banquettes and compargnies, freely and without ſhame, to lette ſcape the winde of the bealie, knowyng that certaine ſhamefatte perſones, ſubiecte to the Collicke, haue died for holdyng the ſaied ventoſitie: As alſo <hi>Cicero</hi> in the xxij. booke of his Epiſtles, ſaith that fartyng ought to be as free as belchyng, after the opinion of the Stoikes.</p>
            <p>You ſhall giue theim to vnderſtande, that you can daiely furniſhe their Pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes with new laied Egges, euery mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng without faile. You ſhall alſo aduertiſe theim, of theim that haue the ſellyng, and diſtribution of them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1323:8"/>You ſhall alſo take heede, that you haue not to deale with ſuche Phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which haue nought els to doe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to walke their Mules, as thei were whiche were obſerued by Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Francis Rables Pentagruell,</hi> to departe out of their lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng at ſixe of the clocke in the mornyng, and to returne at Noone without ſtrikyng of ſtroke. For ſuche are the verie paciences of impacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, by the vnderſtandyng of <hi>Epoptiques</hi> and <hi>Acromatiques</hi> of <hi>Aristotle</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> his Diſciple, whiche thei thought onely worthie to bee read, as writeth <hi>Quintus Curtius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like maner you muſte bee acquainted with xv. or xx. Gainſellers, or Regraters, ſuche as can chatte and babble beſte, and walke aboute all the ſtreates, &amp; the fower corners of the citée, and the moſte famous places of the ſame: as the Burſe, the Pallaice, the greate Haules, the Portes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places of greate reſorte: Aſſuryng theim to furniſhe them daiely of a number of newe laied Egges, whiche thei ſhall ſell and diſtribute to your profite, agreyng with theim for reaſonable price and wages, as ſhalbe ſaied hereafter.</p>
            <p>Hauyng kepte this order, you ſhall bee carefull and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, to cauſe your Egges daiely to bee caried to the Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellers, or women that ſhall ſell them again in the mornyng of the daie followyng. You maie carie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beſte vpon Aſſes. For whiche purpoſe, that Beaſte is verie proper, becauſe of his ſlowe goyng, that he breake not the Egges. But take héede that thei eate no Figges, leaſte you bruſte for laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, as did the Philoſopher <hi>Chryſippus,</hi> as writeth <hi>Diogenes Laertius,</hi> in his booke of the liues of Philoſophers. The like alſo thaunced to <hi>Philomenes,</hi> as writeth <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alerius Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximus,</hi> in his Chapiter of rare kyndes of Death.</p>
            <p>Now it reſteth to make you vnderſtande the profite, that ſhall come vnto you daiely of your ſumme: all charges and expenſes deducted: the rente of your houſe paied, the wages of your ſeruauntes, the Gainſellers contented, the charges of the Aſſe, his kéeper compted, and alſo the graine or corne
<pb facs="tcp:1323:9"/>wherwith your Hennes are ſedde. For of the ſale of Egges is taken no cuſtome, or impoſition, as was in the tyme of Ihon <hi>Ducas</hi> Emperour of Comſtantinople, and ſucceſſour of <hi>Theodoſius Laſcaris,</hi> who was ſo exceſſiue, that in a fewe daies, the Croune of <hi>Irene</hi> the Empreſſe, was thereby mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilouſty enriched in precious ſtones and iewelles, as <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorius</hi> hath left in writyng, in the third booke of the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>Bizantine,</hi> in the chapiter, of the famine of the Turkes.</p>
            <p>You ſhall fell, or cauſe to be ſolde, euery newe laied egge eaſely for ſixe Frenche pence the péece.<note place="margin">ob. and one thirde.</note> For I aſſure you, that within the Citée of Paris, are a thonſande, yea rather twoo thouſande, that will gladly giue a Carolus (whiche is nyne Frenche penuce) for euery newe laied Egge, béeyng thereof aſſured; wherein fee you faile not.</p>
            <p>How many Gentlemenne and Gentlewomen are there, whiche greatly deſire in the Mornyng, to eate a newe laied Egge: How many are there of Citezins, and their wiues, touched with the like deſire: How many old folkes wearie of Fleſhe, could for their Dinner bée contente, with a newe laied Egge or twoo: For you muſt knowe that an Egge, is naturally of good nouriſhemente, wholſome, delicate of ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie digeſtion, and maketh good bloud, as writeth <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Aphrodiſeus</hi> in his ſeconde booke, and xxviij. queſtion of his Problemes. Likewiſe <hi>Albertus Magnus</hi> writeth, that an Egge engendereth in manne, as muche good blood, as is the bigneſſe of the yolke, whiche tourneth almoſte all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bloud.</p>
            <p>I haue yet made no memorie of ſicke folkes, whiche of neceſſitie haue nede of new laied Egges, by the ordinaunce of the Phiſitions, whoſe freendſhip you ſhall entertaine for the ſame purpoſe. The number of the whiche ſicke folkes, I am ſure in the ſaied Citée, will daiely ſurmounte a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande perſones: without ſpeakyng of them that kéepe a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain diet, as well to encreaſe the luſtes of their pleaſures in Venerie, as alſo to reſtore that which ſomtyme by exceſſiue
<pb facs="tcp:1323:9"/>wantonneſſe, thei haue diminiſhed of their ſtrengthe and health. For theſe alſo ſhall haue neede of your marchandize.</p>
            <p>You maie therefore by this deduction, bée aſſured of the vent and ſale, and deliueraunce of your Egges daie by daie as muche as your Hennes ſhall doe their endeuour, orderly to furniſhe your Cuſtomers.</p>
            <p>Now lette vs retourne to our accompt. You can gather no leſſe euery daie of your xij. hundreth Hennes, then eight hundreth Egges: whiche are twoo terces or thirde partes of the number: Leauyng the other terce or thirde parte of your Hennes, in the meane tyme to reſte and repoſe theim ſelues. For the ſeaſon is not euery daie agreable for all He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to laye: Specially in the middeſt of Winter, and other tymes neare vnto that. But you ſhall then helpe them in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng them Fenegreke, commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly called the dredge of Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And alſo Barly halfe ſodde. For theſe thinges kéepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in naturall heate, and cauſe them to laye.</p>
            <p>Eight hundreth Egges, by ſupputation Arithmeticall,<note place="margin">L. Souſes is v. s. vi. d. and ii. third par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of a peny.</note> at ſixe Frenche pence the péece, will yeld. L. Souſes for the hundreth. Whiche in number producte, maketh xx. Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, or Frenche poundes a daie.<note place="margin">xliiii. s. v.d. ii. thirdes.</note> Whiche is, for the ſaied eight hundreth, ſeuen ſcore Frankes the wéeke, and ſeuen chouſande thrée hundreth Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes the yere, of honeſt profite.</p>
            <p>Let vs diuiſe the charges. And that whiche then remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, wée will call the gaines and profite. For the Lawiers ſaie, that wée call nothyng profite, ſauyng what remaineth after the charges deducted: as the famous Lawier <hi>Papinia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> hath well defined in the xxiij. boke of the Pandectes, vnder the title of repetitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of dowrie after the mariage diſſolued.</p>
            <p>Firſt for the penſion of the woorke man,<note place="margin">ii. s. ii. d. and ii. thirdes.</note> and his Houſe for euery daie xx. Souſes: whiche by the yere commeth to thrée hundreth, thrée ſcore and fiue Frankes. I here vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand yeres of the Sunne conſiſting of thrée hundreth, thrée ſcore, and fiue daies.</p>
            <p>For fower Seruauntes or maides, xx. Souſes the daie,
<pb facs="tcp:1323:10"/>which is for eche of them for wages, meate and drinke, fiue Souſes to finde theim ſelues: amountyng in the yere to the like ſumme of thrée hundreth thrée ſcore and fiue Frankes.<note place="margin">xl. lib. xi. s. i. d. &amp; i. third.</note> You knowe how greately ſobrietie is to bee commended in ſeruauntes, bothe menne and women: whiche kicke when thei bée fatte (as doe Monkes in the mewe) and murmure when thei bée full. Emong the whiche, wée meane not ſuche as with pure conſcience, exerciſe them ſelues in their vowe of contemplation of Diuine thynges, in whoſe ſoules, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation taketh perfection, as ſaieth the Diuines. For in all ſortes of men, the beſte ought to bée reſpected, and the worſt noted. Neither yet do I meane, that you ſhould bée ſo ſparyng for the meate of your ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, as was the Abbot of Poſon in Hungarie, who was wont to ſaie that of all the woorkes of his Seruauntes, the mouyng of their Iawes gréeued him moſte: he was ſo filthely coueteous, that he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to ſée his ſeruauntes eate, as writeth <hi>AEneas Syluius</hi> in the xlij. Chapiter of his Hiſtorie of Boheme.</p>
            <p>For the charges of the twoo Aſſes (although Thiſtles growe euery where aboundantly) wée will allowe v. Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes daie: amountyng to fower ſcore and twelue Frankes,<note place="margin">vi. d. and ij. thirdes.</note> and fiue Souſes in the yere. And for the Aſſe kéeper (whom you maie alſo applie to other ſeruice,<note place="margin">x. lib. v. s.</note> after that he hath brought his Egges to the place appointed) who can haue no leſſe then one maide to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie hym, whoſe allowance beyng after the rate of fiue Souſes the daie, commeth to fower ſcore and twelue Franks, and fiue Souſes the yere. Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhall aduertiſe, that he ouercharge not his Aſſes leaſt thei murmure as doe the Monkes vnreformed.</p>
            <p>The Emperour <hi>Augustus Caeſar</hi> after the victorie <hi>Actiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> againſt <hi>Antonius,</hi> iniured by the loue of <hi>Cleopatra</hi> Queene of Egipte, goyng to ſée the Shippes captiue, found ſodain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Aſſe keper, and aſked hym what was his name: Who aunſwered that his name was <hi>Fortunatus:</hi> and the names of his Aſſes, <hi>Victorious.</hi> Thereby gratulating the victorie of
<pb facs="tcp:1323:10"/>the Emperor. You maie féele the profite of your Aſſes with like congratulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and hope of good Fortune and victorie, againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that would haue throwe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you into miſerable po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie: if you folowe your buſineſſe with requiſite diligence as did the ſaied Emperor <hi>Augustus</hi> his warres: Auoidyng ſuche delices &amp; pleaſures, as <hi>Antonius</hi> vſed with <hi>Cleopatra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For meate or féedyng for the Hennes, ſhall ſuffice for the daie twoo quarters of Paris meaſure, as well in Barly as in Otes, Fitches, or Tares: and in Winter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Septier</hi> is the Quarter of Partis v. s. vi. d. and ij. thirdes.</note> bearde or hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Wheate, (whiche in Champaigne is called Saraſine Wheate) after xxv Souſes the Septier or quarter, which by the daie amounteth to L. Souſes: and in the yere ſeuen hundreth, fower ſcore and ſeuen Frankes, and tenne Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, whiche is fower ſcore and vij. li. x. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>As touchyng the Phiſitians, ſome of theim ſelues ſhall haue néede of your marchandice: as thei that haue a Fame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and many little children: whom you muſt viſite wéekely with certain quarterons of newe laied Egges, brought on Thurſdaie for Fridaie &amp; Saterdaie. At Eaſter alſo with certaine Red Egges to preſent to their neighhours, as the reuenue of their practike. But ſuche as haue no familie, and ſeke for wife and houſe, followyng the precepte of <hi>Xenophon</hi> in his <hi>Oeconomiques,</hi> you may to (gratifie then) ſhewe them the increaſe of your Houſebandry, and recite vnto them the pleaſure whiche you receiue therein, to haſten them to caſte theim ſelues into the nette of happie Miſhap, and yet in the meane tyme honour them with ſome pretie Preſentes.</p>
            <p>And if you haue the meanes to recouer Pullettes, or Chikens of the race of he He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, whiche engendered them perfectly formed, ſcrapyng and pepyng, and followyng the Henne, as ſone as thei bee out of the Egge (as rehearſeth <hi>Apuleius</hi> in his booke of the golden Aſſe) you maie thereby giue argument of high Philoſophie of noueltées, vpon the doubte whiche thei make, if the round Egges bryng forthe Cockes, and the long Egges Hennes. Wherein <hi>Albertus</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1323:11"/>
               <hi>Magnus</hi> the Ape of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> doeth contrary his Maiſter, in the ſixth booke of Beaſtes.</p>
            <p>But in the reſolution of this queſtion, you ſhall finde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no leſſe trouble, then in this: whiche is, why there are moe Shéepe then Wolues: Seyng that one Shéepe common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly engendereth not but one, or ſeldome tymes twoo, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Wolfe bryngeth forthe eight or nyne. Againe, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration that for one Wolfe that is killed, a thouſande or twoo thouſande Shéepe goe to the ſlaughter. For the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whiche <hi>Herodotus</hi> bryngeth in his thirde booke of his Muſe of <hi>Thalia,</hi> (where he ſaieth, that Nature hath made fierce and cruell Beaſtes more fruitfull, ſpeakyng of the multitude of Serpentes and Vipers, whiche in <hi>Arabia</hi> kéepe the Trees of Frankenſence) can not bée applied to Wolues, whiche are fierce and rauenyng. But to retourne to our charges.</p>
            <p>For the entertainemente of the ſaied Phiſitians,<note place="margin">xxviii. Iib. xvij. s. ix d. one third.</note> I giue you eſtate of two hundred and thrée ſcore Frankes by the yere. So ſhall your Phiſitians haue no occaſion to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, that thei haue the penſion of Pulters. Of other fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie neuertheleſſe, that he that is founde culpable of falſe reporte, ſhall abide the Iudgement of the Senatour <hi>Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> at the ſiege of <hi>Aquilon,</hi> a Toune of the <hi>Samnites,</hi> of the whiche <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> maketh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion in his vij. booke.</p>
            <p>To the Gainſellers,<note place="margin">vi. d. and. ij. thirdes.</note> you ſhall giue fiue Souſes for a hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. Giuing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> charge, that thei ſell not in your name, any Egges but yours.<note place="margin">xv. s. vi. d. ij. thirdes.</note> Whiche inſumme, ſhalbe by the weeke ſeuen Frankes: and by the yere, three hundred, three ſcore and fiue Frankes.<note place="margin">xl. li. xi. s. i. d. and i. thirde.</note> In the whiche you ſhall doe nothyng co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the opinion of <hi>Socrates,</hi> who blamed theim that bought Marchaundize by groſſe, to ſell theim againe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by retaile, as hurtfull to the common wealthe.</p>
            <p>Then the ſupputation or compte beyng made vppon xx.<note place="margin">x. li. iiii. s. v. d one thirde. viii. hundred xi. li. ii. s. ij. d. two thirdes.</note> Frankes of the ſale of your Egges by the daie, amounting to ſeuen thouſande and thrée hundred Frankes by the yere,
<pb facs="tcp:1323:11"/>wee muſte rebate the ſumme of twoo thouſande, ſeuen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth and three Frankes, and fiue Souſes Tournois, (of currante money) for the expenſes here before compted. So remaineth vnto you the profite by the yere, the ſumme of fower thouſande, fiue hundreth, fower ſcore and xvj. Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and fiue Souſes, whiche is fiue hundreth and xj. li. xxij. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. x. d. and ij. thirdes.</p>
            <p>And when your laiyng Hennes ſhalbe no more then ſixe hundreth a daie, leauyng the other ſixe hundreth in reſte to abide their ſeaſon, yet ſhall remaine vnto you xv. Frankes by the daie: and by the yere, thre thouſande,<note place="margin">xxxiii. s. iii. d</note> fower hundreth fourtie and ſeuen Frankes, three Souſes, and nyne pence, all charges deducted, whiche amounteth to three hundreth fower ſcore and three li. v. d.</p>
            <p>Whiche ſéemeth to me an honeſt gaine and profite, vpon the emploiyng of ſo little a ſumme, and that, without all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Vſurie: By the meanes alſo whereof, you maie feaſte your fréendes, and leade a ioyfull life: I ſaie not prodigall, as of <hi>AEſope</hi> the <hi>Tragike,</hi> with his platter of ſmall Birdes, whereof <hi>Plinie</hi> maketh mention in the tenth booke of his Naturall Hiſtorie. Neither ſo daintie or gluttonous as of <hi>Apitius,</hi> that was in the tyme of the Emperour <hi>Tiberius.</hi> Neither yet ſo ſumptuous &amp; magnificent, as that of <hi>Lucul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> noted of <hi>Plutarche</hi> (in his booke of the liues of famous men) for the Bankett whiche he made vpon the ſodaine, for <hi>Pompeius</hi> and <hi>Cicero:</hi> the expenſe whereof was no leſſe then xij. hundreth and fiftie Crounes, commyng to L. <hi>Sesternes</hi> Romaine. Or that of <hi>Pomponius Atticus.</hi> Againe on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parte. I meane not that your liuyng ſhalbe ſo ſtreight, in frugalitie or ſparyng. as was that of <hi>Curius Dentatus,</hi> who liued with Radiſhe rootes. Or of <hi>Pertinax</hi> who would be ſerued tenne times with one ſalet. Neither ſo vile or ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng, as was <hi>Epaminondas</hi> a greate Lorde of <hi>Thebes,</hi> who kepte his chamber while his apparell was amendyng, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would haue no chaunge.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1323:12"/>But temperate and modeſte, as that of the kynges of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipte, who before thei fell to their meate, diſputed of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and ſobrietie, takyng pleaſure in bankettes, more ioye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, then ſumptuous or exquiſite. And ſo ſhall you not faule into the penaltie of the Lawe Numerall of <hi>Iulius,</hi> who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined a Taxe to be paied of the charges, made in greate fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes and bankettes.</p>
            <p>And for as muche as it maie ſeme a thyng vndecent, that a man ſhould make profeſſion of an Art, or trafique of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaundize, whereof he hath no knowledge, beyng ignorant of the natures and temperatures of the thynges whiche he hath in hande: I will not faile to aduertiſe you of the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, whiche come to He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes and Cockes, and of their reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and when it ſhalbée néedefull to chaunge them, and put others in their places, to th' ende that your number doe not diminiſhe: as you knowe that by ſurrogation, the kyndes of all thynges are preſerued in their beyng, and ſo remaine perpetually: as Diuine <hi>Diotimus</hi> taught <hi>Socrates</hi> in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde booke of the feaſt of <hi>Plato.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their common diſeaſe is the Pippe, whiche is a diſeaſe of the tongue, the ende whereof is thereby hardened, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a griſtle. And thereby alſo the Henne loſeth her taſte bothe in eatyng and drinkyng: and infecteth the other Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſpecially within the houſe, and place of their feding.</p>
            <p>This diſeaſe proceedeth, either of beeyng long without drinkyng of cleane and freaſhe water, or by drinkyng of foule and ſtinkyng water. And to heale it, you muſte take the Henne, and take awaie the ſuperfluitie, which groweth on the tongue hardened at the ende. And then waſhe the tongue and beake with Oile, in the whiche ſhall bée tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a hedde of Garlike. And putte emong their meate Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſacre: and to rubbe the tongue wel with ſpettle or Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, firſt tempered in the mouthe of the ſeruaunt.</p>
            <p>An other diſeaſe, is the Catarre or Rheume, whiche is a fluxion of colde Humours in the hedde of the Hennes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng
<pb facs="tcp:1323:12"/>them to hang their winges, and their creſtes or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes. The remedie is, to trauerſe or ouerthwart ther noſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrilles with a Feather put through them, to open the Flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or Rheume that is ſtopped, and maketh them blinde. It ſhall alſo bée good to warme their drinke in Winter: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuche diſeaſes procéede of cold, or drinkyng of Froſen water, or liyng vnder y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Moone, the mother of al moiſtneſſe.</p>
            <p>Againſt the Lice and vermine, whiche make them leane, féeble, and vnfruitfull, I haue ſhewed you the remedie. But when the diſeaſe is now come, the remedie is to bathe them with a little Wine, or drinke, in the whiche ſhall bée ſodden ſome Comin or Staphiſacre, commonly called the death of Lice, appliyng it to the heddes of little children, with oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</p>
            <p>If you doubt, how I knowe this, not alledgyng any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour for the proofe: you ſhall vnderſtande that I haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it, by practize of the common people, in like maner as the wiſe men emong the Hebrues, named <hi>Cabalistae,</hi> and the like emong the Gaules named <hi>Druydes,</hi> learned their Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences by tradition, from mouthe to mouthe, and from hand to hande without Letters. Whereby is come to paſſe, that in our Feaunce, the gouernmente is more by cuſtomes not written, then by written lawes: As <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in his Commeutaries, of the conqueſt of the Gaules or Frenchemen, in his ſixte Booke.</p>
            <p>The auncientes haue written certain remedies, to kepe the Hennes from the Foxe, as <hi>Palladius</hi> in his Booke of Houſebandrie, teacheth how to rubbe the walles of the Hen houſe, with the gaule of a Foxe and to cutte in little peeces the fleſhe of a Foxe, and to mingle it with the Hennes meat to cauſe the Foxe to abhorre to come neare it, by feelyng the death of his proper kynde, whiche nature can not abide, as writeth <hi>Plinie</hi> in the xxix. booke of his Naturall Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. But the moſte ſoueraigne remedie, is to kéepe faſte and cloſe the doores and windowes in the Night. And that in
<pb facs="tcp:1323:13"/>the Daie. you ſeruauntes often tymes come, and goe in all places and corners of your cloſe. And that neare vnto it, or the Henne houſe, bée no heapes of woodde, buſhes, or ſtones, where ſuche beaſtes maie bée hidde or harboured. For, the beaſtes whiche liue by rapte, haue euer a certaine feare ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with their craftineſſe, and deſire of rauenyng.</p>
            <p>Aboute the tyme of Autumne, you ſhall euery yere draw a hundred or twoo hundred of the eldeſt of your He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, and ſuche as haue their clawes longeſt, and groſſeſt. In place of the whiche, you ſhall put yonger of ſuche ſorte or qualitie, as I haue before deſcribed.</p>
            <p>If peraduenture you be of opinion, to kepe your Egges of one ſeaſon for an other, you muſt laye them in order vpon ſheaues or ſtrawe verie freſhe, with the ſharpe ende vpward or to laye them in Paniers in like maner. And that thei bée well couered with ſtrawe, that thei bee not tourned by too muche heate, or cold. And if you wil choſe the beſte for your fréendes, take <hi>Candida. Longa, Noua</hi> (that is) White, Long, and New, folowyng the opinion of the Schoole of <hi>Salerne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other twoo Acres whiche remaine aboute youre yarde, courte, or place incloſed, ſhall be commodious to ſow Barly, whiche is a graine verie proper for the noriture of He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes. And if you can recouer Barly of the ſede of <hi>AEthiope</hi> whereas dwell the Iewes of the ligue of <hi>Dan, Nephthalin, Gad, &amp; Aſſer,</hi> neare to the riuer of <hi>Sabbatique</hi> (whiche <hi>Moiſes</hi> affirmeth to bee the Riuer in the holie ſcripture called <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zan</hi>) it ſhall bee ſinguler good, becauſe one graine thereof bryngeth forthe an hundred, as <hi>Eldad Damus</hi> the Hebrewe hath written in his brief Hiſtorie of the Empire of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes incloſed in <hi>AEthiope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will write vnto you more amplie of the other profites, whiche concerne the noriture of Hennes, and of what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties thei are, and what one maie drawe of their ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But my ende hath been none other, then to giue aduiſe, how for a little ſumme of money, &amp; little trauaile, you maie
<pb facs="tcp:1323:13"/>gette greate profite: to the ende that you maie the more eaſely forgette your loſſes, and accuſtome your ſelf to the noiſe and cluckyng of your Hennes: and not to ſeeme more delicate, then was the good Philoſopher <hi>Socrates,</hi> who bore it eaſely, becauſe thei laied hym Egges: as he bore pacient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the murmuryng and ſcoldyng of his wife <hi>Xantippe,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe bore hym children.</p>
            <p>You maie euery daie ſee your menage, or Houſebandrie. And (as did the <hi>Peripatetici</hi>) walke aboute the cloſes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places: and conſider the endeuour of your ſeruauntes. Whom alſo by this meanes, you ſhall make more carefull and diligente: and your He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes better intreated, accordyng to the <hi>Apophthegme</hi> whiche ſaieth: That the eye of the mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, maketh the ſeruaunt prompter, and the horſe fatter: as alſo <hi>Aristotle</hi> maketh mention in his firſte booke of <hi>Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomikes.</hi> But how ſo euer it bee, directe your Houſebandrie in ſuche order, that bones bee not giuen to Aſſes, and Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to Dogges.</p>
            <p>The Maide ſeruaunte, or Chamberlaine of <hi>Prometheus</hi> (named <hi>Experience</hi>) who ſerued hym, after that he hadde brought from Heauen the liberall Sciences, and to whom when he drewe neare to death, he gaue them by Teſtament, maie in ſhort tyme aſſure you, either to continew this mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize and trafique, or to leaue it. For ſhe (Experience I meane) is one of the chief Seruauntes, whiche you muſte haue, with other diligence compaignie.</p>
            <p>You ought not to take it gréeuouſly, to leaue your dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng place, and accuſtomed pleaſaunte ayre, or your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, couſins, or frendes. For you knowe well the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities whiche ciuill warre bringeth, the whiche (as wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Cicero</hi> to <hi>Marcus Marcellus,</hi> in the fowerth booke of his familer Epiſtles) is no leſſe lamentable, then the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie gotten by ſheadyng of domeſticall bloud. And therefore not without reaſon ſaieth the Prouerbe, That warre is pleaſaunte to ſuche, as hath no experience thereof. The
<pb facs="tcp:1323:14"/>whiche ſaiyng, <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> a rare man in all kinde of learnyng hath in his <hi>Chiliades,</hi> dilated by many examples: As you maie alſo eaſely iude at this preſent. You knowe alſo that the Marchaunt to flie pouertie, hazardeth hym ſelf by lande and ſea, and leaueth his natiue Ayre and Countrie.</p>
            <p>And for the doubte that you maie haue, not to bee aſſured in peaceable poſſeſſion of your incloſed ground, againſt the violence of Théeues or Souldiers: I would wiſhe you for the garde thereof, either the wakyng Serpente, whiche kept the Gardens of <hi>Heſperides</hi> (famous for the golden ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les) ſlaine by <hi>Hercules</hi> of <hi>Thebes,</hi> or the furious Bulles, whche kepte the Golden Fléeſe in the Ile of <hi>Colchos,</hi> vnder kyng <hi>AE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tas</hi> the Father of <hi>Medea,</hi> whiche were ouercome and tamed by <hi>Iaſon</hi> of <hi>Theſſalia,</hi> at the voiage of the <hi>Argonau</hi> tae. Haue recourſe to the <hi>Metamorphoſes</hi> of <hi>Ouid,</hi> in the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werth and ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th booke. But better then all this, ſhall ſerue for your ſecuritie, a Tablet of three flower de Liees (the Kynges Seale) autoriſed by the kyng: whiche ſhall bee of greater efficacie, then any other ſaucgarde that you can deſire.</p>
            <p>For finall counſail, I praie you continue in the loue and feare of GOD, obeiſaunce to your Prince, and his Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, reuerence to all ſuperious, with pacience of your loſſes, to occupie your trade without fraude, and you ſhall finde multiplication of all your goodes. And then (as ſaith <hi>Iuuenal</hi> in his thirde <hi>Satyre</hi>) you maie ſay, that your are the ſonne of a white Henne.</p>
            <p>But when you ſhall bee knowen to doe ſeruice, to ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a common wealthe, as is the Citée of Paris (whiche ſurmounteth all thoſe that haue been Famous emong the Greekes) and that you haue giuen the firſte entrie, and (as ſaieth the Prouerbe) broken the Iſe to others, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe your enemies ſhall bee repulſed, as were thei of <hi>Furius Creſſinus</hi> Citezin of Roome, enuied of his neighbours, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that of a little he raiſed more Gaine, then thei d. d of
<pb facs="tcp:1323:14"/>muche Tillage. For the whiche thei imputed vnto him, that he vſed Witcherafre, and Inchauntmente. Who bringyng forthe his Inſtrumentes of Houſebandrie, his diligent ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, and alſo his owne Daughter moſte ſkilfull in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, was diſcharged of all ſuche ſuſpicious, and of all men greately commended, as writeth <hi>Titus Liuius.</hi> And further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, your felicitie and proſperitie, ſhalbe a paſſion to your enemies, as chaunceth to all enuious perſones.</p>
            <p>I knowe other experiences verie prompte. But of no greater gaine then ſixe Frankes the daie,<note place="margin">xiii. s. iiii. d.</note> all charges de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted. Therefore, if my firſte inſtructions ſeme not agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto your nature, aduertiſe me thereof, that I maie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte vnto you an other waie more eaſie, and no leſſe delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, though of leſſe profite.</p>
            <p>Peraduenture ſome will thinke this Counſaill verie ſtraunge and ridiculous, and perhaps of difficult executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. To thinke it ſtraunge, there is no greate reaſon, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering that nouriſhyng of Hennes for honeſt gaines, is no newe or ſtraunge thing, if we beleue that whiche <hi>Celius Rhodoginus,</hi> a worthie Autor, hath written in his 14. booke of Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: That in the Ile of <hi>Delos</hi> (otherwiſe called <hi>Ortygia</hi> for the abundance of Qualies) beyng one of the moſte famous of the <hi>Cyclades</hi> in the ſea <hi>Aegaeum,</hi> were founde many that made eſtate and trafique of the nouriſhement of Hennes, for gaine and profite. Who were ſo well exerciſed herein, and in the knowledge of their He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, that onely vpon the ſight of an Egge, thei could eaſily iudge what Hen it came from. Therefore, that ſellyng of Egges hath euer been a thyng commonly vſed: haue recourſed to the Impoſt, which was in the tyme of the Emperour <hi>Honorius,</hi> as is ſaied heretofore.</p>
            <p>As touchyng mockers, no man can eſtabliſhe any thing ſo good, or well ordered, that the Mocker ſhall not bite, when Enuie hath made impreſſion in his fooliſhe Braine, and hath there taken vp his ſod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yng, to torment his Hoſte.</p>
            <p>And to reſolue you of ſuche difficulties, let vs take holde
<pb facs="tcp:1323:15"/>of the ſaiyng of <hi>Agathon</hi> a yong gentleman, in the Oration whiche he made of Loue in the feaſte of <hi>Plato,</hi> ſaiyng: That we ought more to feare the iudgement of a fewe wiſe men, then of many ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fooles and mockers. For Wiſemen ſlowlie giue the looſe bridle to their congues, but vſe their wordes with iudgemente: as alſo writeth <hi>Cicero</hi> in his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for <hi>Plancius,</hi> ſaiyng: That the iudgemente of tenne wiſe and graue men in one Citée, importeth more then the iudgemente of all the common people, who for the moſte parte, iudge without counſaill or reaſon.</p>
            <p>If any maune ſhall ſaie, that the inuention of this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile is old: I confeſſe vnto you, that I am not the firſte rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher hereof, as was <hi>Carbilius</hi> of the firſte letters at Rome, or the firſte Schoolemaiſter: yet hath it not been practiſed in our tyme. And as writeth the Poet <hi>Horatius,</hi> Many thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are renewed, whiche tyme hath deuoured, and buried as deade, the whiche againe in tyme, ſhall bee drouned in the riuer of Obliuion, and ſhall againe retourne to their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate by courſe, as doe in maner all worldly thinges, as wiſe Salomon alſo witneſſeth.</p>
            <p>Aſſure your ſelf my deare fréede, that <hi>Magnifico Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret,</hi> or any other Alchimiſte, haue not with their Fornaces and Alembikes, drawne more profite by the Philoſophers Stone, then you ſhall drawe out of the bealie of your Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, if you will ioyne pleaſure with paine. And ſo ſhall you bée out of the daunger, into whiche ſuche Alchimiſtes fall, who oftentymes conſume their Patrimonie, and blowe it awaie with Bellowes. But euer beware the Foxe. In the meane tyme, you ſhall receiue of your fréende this little gift ſuche as it is, in hope hereafter to recouer of hym ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thyng, when occaſion doeth ſerue: whiche (occaſion) you muſt take by the haire before, that it ſcape not from you.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, for the ende of this accompte, you muſt arme your ſelf with pacience, when affliction is ſent, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide pouertie (the enemie of all good maners) by exerciſe
<pb facs="tcp:1323:15"/>of honeſte and profitable frugalitie in vſyng the thynges, whiche you haue gotten by your labour: and therewith alſo a reputation not bulgare, whiche ſhall bée bruted through all Fraunce, for the noueltie of your enterpriſe. Whereof ſome will take ſuche pleaſure, as maie moue the ſeuere <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toes</hi> to laughyng, and raiſe the Melancholike Milte of wée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng <hi>Democrites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And finally, you ſhall herewith receiue the contentation of your louyng fréende, with this pleaſaunte preſent, to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate the ſorrowes of theſe Cloudie tymes, and to put you in good comforte of better hope in tyme to come.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Hatchyng of Egges without Hennes, as writeth <hi>Ioannes Porta</hi> in his ſeconde Booke of Magike Naturall.</head>
               <p>TAke the dounge of Pigeons or Hennes, beaten into pouder, and finely Sifted. Then laye the Egges in ſuche ſort, that one touche not an other for breaking. And ſée thei bée well couered with the ſaied dounge, bothe vnder and aboue, in cloſe Panniers or Coopes, commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for the purpoſe, ſo that the rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der or bigger ende of the Egges bée dounwarde. But firſte, you muſte laie a bedde of Hennes feathers, and thereon the dounge: and likewiſe an other ranke or bedde of feathers vppon the dounge that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth the Egges. This doen, you ſhall euery xxiiij. houres tourne the Egges, that thei maie equally receiue the heate. Thei muſt thus bée kept, in a place of temperate heate. And when twentie daies are paſte, if you ſhall perceiue that the chickins ſtrike the ſhell with their billes, harken if thei péepe. For often it chaunceth, that for the thickneſſe of the ſkinne or filme, thei can not breake foorth. Then helpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with takyng of the ſhell. And immediatly bryng the Henne vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The like maie be doen in a warme Ouen, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the meaſure and proportion of Natural heate. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:1323:16"/>alſo in hotte horſe dounge, with like diligence of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuryng, and conſeruyng the heate, with adding of newe and pure dounge euery ſeuenth daie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cardanns</hi> in his xij. booke <hi>De Subtilitate,</hi> writeth muche in like maner: But ſaieth that you muſte firſte make twoo Cuſſhions or Pillowes, filled with Hennes dounge, beaten into fine pouder and ſifted. Then by ſowyng, or other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes faſtenyng on the Pillowes, He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes fethers, bothe great and ſmall of good thickeneſſe, and laye the Egges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene theim in a warme place &amp;c. as before. He writeth that in the greate Citie of <hi>Alkair</hi> or <hi>Babilonia Noua</hi> in Egipte, thei vſe thus to hatche Egges in greate mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
